XMLPatterns.com

Container Element

Abstract

A container has multiple elements as child elements. A new element type is created to group related elements. This is a very general pattern and many other patterns specialize this one.

Problem

There are multiple elements that occur at the same level within a document. These elements can be separated into distinct groups.

Context

There are multiple elements that can occur as child elements of a single, higher level element, and some of these elements are related.

Forces

Documents need structure, and this is the easiest way to add structure to a document.

Solution

Create a new element that contains some of the multiple child elements.

Examples

        

<ComputerConfiguration>
<RAM>128 MB</RAM>
<WordProcessor>WordPerfect</WordProcessor>
<HardDriveSize>8GB</HardDriveSize>
<XMLParser>Xerces</XMLParser>
</ComputerConfiguration>

        
      

The above document describes a computer's configuration. If however processing software was only interested in the hardware aspects of the configuration it would need to check all of the elements and extract the RAM and HardDriveSize elements. Compare this to the following:

        

<ComputerConfiguration>
<Software>
<Wordprocessor>Wordperfect</Wordprocessor>
<XMLParser>Xerces</XMLParser>
</Software>
<Hardware>
<RAM>128 MB<RAM>
<HardDriveSize>8 GB</HardDriveSize>
</Hardware>
</ComputerConfiguration>

        
      

In this example the software and hardware aspects of the configuration are separated. Processing software that need to extract individual aspects can do so easily.

Discussion

This pattern adds a level of abstraction to the structure of a document. This abstraction can be used to simply provide grouping of elements as in the Examples section. This grouping provides additional semantic information about the data.

This extra element can also be a useful place to provide metadata about the individual group of data.

Related Patterns

The

Marketplace

pattern can be used if there is more than one category that can apply to each type.

The

Head-Body

pattern uses two specific types of Container Elements, one for metadata and one for content.

The

Collection Element

is a container for single type of element.

Known Uses

The Isogen whitepaper Object-Oriented SGML

Deconstructing SGML for Storage Section

(http://www.isogen.com/papers/oosgml.html#storage) contains an an excellent example of where a container was used to help in the storage and retrieval of data.

References

See

Structuring XML Documents

, Section 5.2.1: Containers.

XMLPatterns.com

Declare Before First Use

Abstract

Elements which are referenced by another part of a document should be found earlier in the document than the first place they are referenced.

Problem

Often an element will refer to another one; this is what the ID and IDREF attributes in XML are used for. A common example is a footnote element. When processing software encounters an reference to an element that has not yet been processed, it often has to do more processing.

Context

This pattern applies to a wide variety of document types. It is common to have elements reference one another.

Forces

Ease of processing is effected by element order. Having elements in the correct order can make processing easier.

Solution

Ensure that the elements are ordered so that elements are encountered before they are referred to. This gives the processing software a better chance of doing a single pass traversal of the document.

Examples

        

<!DOCTYPE Doc [

<!ELEMENT Person (Adress*, BillToAddress, ShipToAddress)>

<!ELEMENT Address (#PCDATA)>
<!ATTLIST Address id IDREF #REQUIRED >

<!ELEMENT BillToAddress EMPTY>
<!ATTLIST BillToAddress address IDREF #REQUIRED>

<!ELEMENT ShipToAddress EMPTY>
<!ATTLIST ShipToAddress address IDREF #REQUIRED>

]>

<Doc>
<Person>
<Address id="1">
123 Main St, New York NY
</Address>
<Address id="2">
2001 5th Ave, New York NY
</Address>
<BillToAddress address="1"/>
<ShipToAddress address="2"/>
</Person>
</Doc>

        
      

Discussion

Stream based processors are popular, particularly when documents are very large, and may take up large amounts of memory, or when speed of processing is essential. It is often difficult to use stream based processing if elements that are needed to process a section of the document do not appear until after the place they are needed. This requires a forward-looking mechanism that goes against the principle of stream based processing.

Related Patterns

Consider this pattern when applying the

Referenced Note

. The

Metadata First

is very similar to this patterns, except it deals with metadata instead of general elements as this pattern does.

Known Uses

XMLPatterns.com

Domain Element

Abstract

A concept from domain analysis is made into an element.

Problem

A concept in the domain needs to be recognized as a distinct unit of information when processing it.

Context

Every document has a domain, and every domain has unique concepts.

Forces

Data needs to be structured in order to be processed.

Solution

Concepts from the domain become elements in the document.

Examples

In a payroll processing system, Employees, Hourly Wage, and Hours Worked are all concepts from the domain. These can all be made into elements in a document type used for dealing with the payroll.

        

<Employee id="62537">
<HourlyWage>25.00</HourlyWage>
<HoursWorked>40</HoursWorked>
</Employee>

        
      

Discussion

Object Oriented Analysis and Entity-Relational DataBase modeling techniques are useful for finding domain concepts.

Granularity of object needs to be thought about. Too granular results in more markup and more processing, if elements are not granular enough, extra parsing needs to be done by the application.

Related Patterns

Known Uses

All document types are full of Domain Elements.

XHTML is used for markup of documents to be displayed so it contains elements for things such as titles, headings, and paragraphs.

The Information and Content Exchange (ICE) Protocol

(http://www.icestandard.org/) is used for distributing web content, so it contains elements such as sender, receiver, request and response.

XMLPatterns.com

Generic Element

Abstract

To provide flexibility to users of the document, designers can provide an element type that is very generic. The use of the generic element is not well specified by the documents type. This allows for authors to use the document type in ways that may not have been foreseen.

Problem

The designer does not know exactly what the users of the document intend to do with the document and needs to add flexibility to the document type.

Context

This is useful in general purpose document types, when flexibility is needed.

Forces

Flexibility is required to make some document types useful. This pattern can effect the ease of processing of the document type.

Solution

Provide a new element that does not have a specific meaning.

Examples

        

<Paragraph>
Albert Camus' <General type="book">The Stranger</General>
is an existentialist novel.
</Paragraph>

        
      

Discussion

Not providing enough flexibility can make document authors use the wrong element for markup. This can lead to documents that are difficult to understand, and mistakes in processing occur.

This flexibility can make processing software difficult to create. Adding

Role Attribute

s to the generic element can help provide the processing software some clues as to how to process the element.

Related Patterns

A

Role Attribute

is often used in conjunction with Generic Elements.

Known Uses

The div and span elements in XHTML.

References

The Fielded Text example from

The XML & SGML Cookbook

page 2-48, uses Generic Elements.

XMLPatterns.com

Marketplace

Abstract

Instead of organizing objects in a hierarchical fashion, objects are organized in a linear way, with signs on each object to indicate its classifications.

Problem

A natural way to use mark up to classify objects is to use a container for each new type in the classification.

        

<Employees>
<Managers>
<Person type="salaried">
Riff Raff
</Person>
<Person type="contractor">
Frank Furter
</Person>
</Managers>
<Workers>
<Person type="salaried">
Brad Majors
</Person>
<Person type="contractor">
Janet Weiss
</Person>
</Workers>
</Employees>

        
      

This can lead to problems, if processing software needs to find all of the employees, or just the salaried employees, it needs to iterate through two different lists, the managers and the workers.

Context

Any place where data can be organized by more than one type.

Forces

Ease-of-processing can be greatly affected by the way that elements are organized. Ease-of-Authoring can also be a problem, pick one structural organization can lead to awkward groupings of elements, and the choice of structure may seem arbitrary.

Solution

The objects to be modeled can all be grouped at the same level, and the categorization can be done with attributes on the element. This allows multiple characteristics of the objects to be modeled without enforcing a possibly artificial hiearchy on the objects.

Examples

The following model can be contrasted to the sample in the problem section, which uses a tree structure to model employees. Each employee can have two different types, whether they are Salaried or Contractors and whether they are Workers or Managers. In the tree structure, one of the types, the Worker/Manager distinction is given more importance than the Salaried/Contractor. Extra effort would be required to extract just the Salaried employees.

The sample below uses the Marketplace pattern to organize the same data into a flatter structure. In this organization both types are given equal precedence, and both types are equally easy to process.

        

<Employees>
<Person type="salaried" level="manager">
Riff Raff
</Person>
<Person type="contractor" level="manager">
Frank Furter
</Person>
<Person type="salaried" level="worker">
Brad
</Person>
<Person type="contractor" level="worker">
Janet
</Person>
</Employees>

        
      

Discussion

This pattern results in a organization that can make mapping to database tables easier. The elements in the marketplace are equivalent to rows in a table, while the attributes are the columns. A more hierarchical structure can be harder to map to databases.

Related Patterns

The Marketplace is often contained in a

Collection Element

.

Known Uses

References

See:The Microsoft whitepaper

Serializing Graphs of Data in XML

(http://www.infoloom.com/gcaconfs/WEB/TOC/t0302_.HTM) for a discussion of representing graph structure such as RDBMS tables in XML.

XMLPatterns.com

Metadata First

Abstract

Metadata should appear in a document before the data which it is about.

Problem

Many processors (for example SAX based parsers) are stream based. That is, the document is processed as it is read in, the whole document is never held in memory at the same time. If a piece of metadata appears after the data it refers to, the application software will need to store the data, then read the metadata in order to know what to do with the data.

Context

Anywhere in the document that metadata appears.

Forces

The ease and speed of processing a document can be effected by the order in which the structures of the document appear.

Solution

Always make sure that metadata appears in a document before the data it refers to. This can be done whether the metadata is attribute data or element data.

For example, with the following code,

          

<Heading>
This is a new section<Font size="3"/>
</Heading>

          
        

If the processing software were trying to send this information to a printer, it would need to save the text of the heading, read in the font size, send the font size command to the printer, and then send the text to the printer. If the font element appeared before the text, there would be no need to save the text.

Examples

This example shows a table element with the height and width elements appearing before the actual data of the table. This allows the processing software to start rendering the table as the data is read in. If the height and width of the table came after the table data, the processing software would need to read in and save all the data before starting to display it.

        

<Table>
<height unit="pixels">100</height>
<width unit="pixels">100</width>
<Row><Col>2</Col><Col>3</Col></Row>
<Row><Col>8</Col><Col>7</Col></Row>
</Table>

        
      

Discussion

Placing the metadata before the data that it is about will often simplify processing software. This is also often a natural way for people to think about the data, making documents easier to read and author.

Related Patterns

The ordering of the head and body element in the

Head-Body

pattern is an application of this pattern.

Known Uses

In XHTML The head, which contains metadata, and body which contains the content are always in that order. The table elements contain size and spacing data in the attributes of the table element, which places it before the data, and the caption and column width and spacing data appears before the table data itself.

XMLPatterns.com

Optional Container Element

Abstract

When creating large DTDs with many logical units authors might be required to learn a large number of these logical units to know how to use the DTD. By hiding the details of optional parts of the DTD beneath optional elements, some of this complexity can be reduced.

Problem

In a DTD with many logical units, an author of a document can be overwhelmed with the number of choices that have to be made.

Context

In large, general-purpose DTDs where many logical units are presented, and more than one of the units is optional. The document will be authored by humans.

Forces

In order to make DTDs applicable in many situations, large numbers of logical units need to appear in the DTD. However, presenting large numbers of logical units makes the DTD more difficult to learn by authors of documents.

Solution

Hide related parts of a document that may never be needed by an author of a document beneath an element type. Any details of the structure of a document that are optional in a document can be grouped together as attributes and children elements of a single element. If an author never uses this branch of the document, none of the logical units within that branch need to be known to the other.

Examples

Lets create a DTD that allows an author to create notes that can be a note to oneself, or an email. The DTD might look like this:

        

<!ELEMENT Note (NoteToSelf | Email )>
<!ELEMENT NoteToSelf (Body)>
<!ELEMENT Body (#PCDATA)>
<!ELEMENT Email (Recipient+, CC*, BCC*, Body)>
<!ELEMENT Recipient (#PCDATA)>
<!ELEMENT CC (#PCDATA)>
<!ELEMENT BCC (#PCDATA)>

        
      

If the author of these documents only had to be create notes to himself, he would never need to be aware of the elements that are required in the Email branch of the DTD. He would create his document like this:

        

<Note>
<NoteToSelf>
<Body>This is my note</Body>
</NoteToSelf>
<Note>

        
      

Although the DTD contains 7 elements, the author would only have to use three elements: Note, NoteToSelf and Email. The author would never be required to use the Email element and would not even have to be aware of the existence of the remaining three elements.

Discussion

Once the Optional Group Pattern is applied, the learning requirements placed on the author of documents is reduced. Application of this pattern can however lead to an increase in the overall number of logical units in the DTD. The above note DTD could have been written as follows:

        

<!ELEMENT Note (Recipient?, CC?, BCC?, Body)>
<!ELEMENT Body (#PCDATA)>
<!ELEMENT Recipient (#PCDATA)>
<!ELEMENT CC (#PCDATA)>
<!ELEMENT BCC (#PCDATA)>

        
      

This actually reduces the number of logical units in the DTD from 7 to 5, but makes things more complicated for users who just want to write notes to themselves, because they now have to be aware of the Recipient, CC, and BCC elements. The Optional Group hides complexity from the authors of documents by introducing optional elements that hide the details of a piece of the document that the author might not care about. By introducing a single higher level element, the details of many logical units may be hidden from the author, thereby reducing the learning requirements of the author.

Related Patterns

This Optional Group is similar to the

Choice Reducing Container

in that they both hide logical units of a document from the author by introducing new element types. Existing elements are group together beneath the new element. The major difference between the two is the context they are used in. The Choice Group relates elements that are all choices in a content group while the Optional Group relates optional elements from the content group.

Known Uses

This DTD fragment was taken from XBEL:

        

<!ELEMENT xbel (title?, info?, desc?, (%nodes.mix;)*)>
<!ELEMENT info (metadata+)>
<!ELEMENT metadata EMPTY>
<!ATTLIST metadata owner CDATA #REQUIRED>

        
      

When generating an XBEL document, the info element is not required. This means that if the author was never interested in creating an info element, he would not need to know about the info element, the metadata element, or the owner attribute, thus eliminating 3 logical units from what the author needs to learn.

XMLPatterns.com

Reuse Document Types

Abstract

If document types already exist for the job at hand, they can be reused completely or parts of them can be reused.

Problem

A new set of data needs to be marked up with XML and a document type is needed.

Context

This applies to almost every project. Before starting to create a new document type, existing ones that can be used should be looked for.

Forces

Reusing existing data cuts down on development costs and times.

Using industry standard document types increases chances that existing tools can be used out of the box, and allows for future interoperability.

Solution

Reuse an existing document type. If an industry standard document type already exists, it should be reused.

Examples

Discussion

Before anybody creates a new document type, existing document types should be investigated.

Complete Reuse

Ideally a document type will exist that precisely matches the needs of the project. This can be beneficial in many areas:

Decrease development time and cost
Reuse of Experience. Often developers of existing documents are groups of experienced experts who have put significant time into the development of the document type, and will produce high quality document types.
Interoperability. Use of industry standard document types will increase the chance that the system will interoperate with other systems.

Partial Reuse

If existing document types do not exactly match the needs of the project, they can be partially reused. Modification can be made to document types to allow this partial reuse. The easiest way to do this is simply to edit the existing document type. Some document types may allow for customization through techniques such as

Extensible Content Model

. Partially reusing document types still has the benefits of decreasing development time and cost, and reusing experience, but will not allow for interoperabilty. If interoperabilty is a desired goal of the system, modification of existing document types must be looked at very carefully.

Related Patterns

Known Uses

Many of the document types found in the references section are being reused in multiple projects.

References

There are several sources of existing schemas on the web:

XML.org's Catalog

(http://www.xml.org/xml/registry.jsp)

Schema.net

(http://www.schema.net/)

XMLPatterns.com

Role Attribute

Abstract

Sometimes the designer of a DTD can not foresee all of the needs that the author of a document will have. In order to give the author flexibility an attribute that specifies a role can be included on some of the elements.

Problem

Specialization of the document type sometimes needs to be made by an author. It is impossible for the designer of the DTD to foresee all of the uses that the authors have in mind. The designer may not even know where in the document the specialization will need to take place.

Context

For any document type that is intended for use outside a very limited context, users need flexibility to include uses which the designed of the document type has not foreseen.

Forces

By definition, document types constrain the choices that a document author can make. This constraint can at times be too limiting. Document users need flexibility to use the document type in ways not foreseen by the designer of the document type.

Solution

An attribute is created which can further describe the element. This role attribute further specializes the use of the Element.

Examples

        

<!ELEMENT Document (Paragraph)*>
<!ELEMENT Paragraph (#PCDATA)>
<!ATTLIST Paragraph Role CDATA>

        
      

Using the above DTD the author can create a document like this:

        

<Document>
<Paragraph Role="warning">
Do not attempt this at home.
</Paragraph>
<Paragraph>
The following is a set of
instructions for creating
a bungee jumping cord from
elastic bands ...
</Paragraph>
</Document>

        
      

The author intends for the "Do not attempt this at home" paragraph to appear emphasized in some way, for example in bold or in a different color. The DTD designer would have had no way of knowing the special needs of the author of the document, so a Role Attribute was placed on the paragraph, to allow for different types of paragraphs to exist.

Discussion

Including role attributes allows the author to have a great deal of flexibility. The flexibility may make the creation of processing software very difficult. Processing software will not be able to know in advance the intention of the author. However, by allowing customization of processing software through the use of scripts or stylesheet, this can be a very powerful pattern. Much of the power of

XSLT

(http://www.w3.org/TR/xslt) and

CSS

(http://www.w3.org/Style/) comes from being able to add Role Attributes.

Role attributes can be used to extend the document type without changing the structure of documents. This can help extend the life of the document type between revisions, and can be used to prototype new features of the document type.

Related Patterns

Role attributes are almost always used on

Generic Element

types. Generic Elements are created when the designer of a document type does not know all of the uses of that element, and the Role Attribute allows the author of a document to make the element more specialized to his or her use of the element.

Known Uses

XHTML uses several role attributes including class and meta element in XHTML.

The

XMLspec DTD role attribute

(http://www.w3.org/XML/1998/06/xmlspec-report-v21.htm#AEN620) shows a typical usage of this pattern.

XMLPatterns.com

Universal Root

Abstract

Provide a single root element that contains an option of multiple elements. Often used for different transaction types within a single document type.

Problem

There are several different types of document that need to be processed. Providing a single root element allows for all of the different types of document to be defined by a single DTD. When a processor receives this document, it will know which type of document to expect by inspecting the child element of the root element.

Context

Universal Root is useful when a system has several different, but related, document types to be processed. A transactional processor would be an example of such a system.

Forces

Having multiple, distinct document types can increase the maintenance burden of a system. Document types that may be related, but are declared in separate files can start to stray from commonalities that can be taken advantage of.

Solution

Create a document type that has a single root element.

Examples

        

<!ELEMENT Transaction
(AddAddress | RemoveAddress | UpdateAddress)>

<!ELEMENT AddAddress
(AddressBookEntry)>

<!ELEMENT RemoveAddress
(AddressID)>

<!ELEMENT UpdateAddress
(AddressID, AddressBookEntry)>


<Transaction>
<AddAddress>
<AddressBookEntry> ... </AddressBookEntry>
</AddAddress>
</Transaction>

        
      

In this example an online address book application is being developed. There are several transactions that can take place, lick adding new entries, deleting entries, updating entries.

Discussion

This allows a way for several related types of documents to be grouped into a single document type structure. A processing system will always know which DTD to expect, but can still handle the documents differently based on the first nested element type. This makes sharing common definitions between the different document easy.

This is also a way that multiple XML document can be gathered into a single larger document. For example a log file might consist of several fragments, for example:

        

<Log>
<Time>Jan 15, 1999 10:58AM</Time>
<Event>Startup</Event>
</Log>
<Log>
<Time>Jan 15, 1999 11:02AM</Time>
<Event>Message Received from Bob</Event>
</Log>
...

        
      

Since there is no root element in the file it cannot be processed "as is". To process this, one can prepend a start tag, for example "<LogFile>", in front of the file, and append the end tag "</LogFile>" to the end of the file to be able to process it as a single XML document.

Related Patterns

Multi Root Document Types

and

Multiple Document Types

are alternatives to this pattern.

Known Uses

XMLPatterns.com

Use XML

Abstract

XML technology can be used to represent structured information. This pattern helps determine when XML is an appropriate solution.

Problem

When data in a system needs to be imported or exported, it needs some type of representation. There are many possible representations for example: Comma Separated Values, Java Object Serialization, Proprietary Binary Formats, HTML, CORBA IIOP Streams, RDBMS tables, and of course XML. Choosing the proper representation for the data can be difficult.

Context

XML can be an appropriate choice when one or more of the following is needed:

Content needs to be separate from its formatting.
Data is shared between computers, applications or organizations.
Human readable representation is needed.
Readily available tools and resources.

There are some situations where XML may not be a good choice, among them is systems where:

Terseness is important.
In a homogeneous environment.

Forces

There are many forces to take into account when considering a data representation. Among the ones that XML can provide are simplicity, openness, extensibility, interoperability, and a technology with proven use.

Solution

Use XML for data representations.

Examples

Discussion

It is impossible to have a complete discussion of the factors involved in make the decision of a data representation in the space of a single pattern, but it can try to provide some pointers.

Related Patterns

All other patterns in this language depend on first using this pattern, because they assume that XML is being used.

Known Uses

There are many places where XML is being used successfully. Here is a small sampling of them.

Data syndication. XML has been popular in this area, and several XML languages have been developed for this purpose.

The Information and Content Exchange (ICE) Protocol

(http://www.icestandard.org)

moreover.com

(http://w.moreover.com/) provides news feeds in several different XML flavors.
News can be syndicated to browsers via

Rich Site Summary

(http://www.xml.com/pub/a/2002/12/18/dive-into-xml.html)

Data exchange protocols for transport of messages from one system to another across a network.

SOAP (Simple Object Access Protocol)

(http://www.w3.org/TR/SOAP/)

Configuration files J2EE uses

Deployment Descriptors

(http://java.sun.com/xml/ns/j2ee/) to configure various components
Test Scripting The

XML Test Suite

(http://xmltestsuite.sourceforge.net/)
Log files The

LOGML

(http://www.cs.rpi.edu/~puninj/LOGML/) specification is designed to describe log reports of web servers
Web content management

See

Ronald Bourret's Content Management Systems page

(http://www.rpbourret.com/xml/ProdsCMS.htm)

Wireless Application Data (WAP)

(http://www.openmobilealliance.org/)

References

For more information:

Simon St. Laurent's Essay -

Why XML?

(http://www.simonstl.com/articles/whyxml.htm) .

A whitepaper by Bob Schloss at the IBM developerWorks site

Ten best bets for XML applications

(http://www.digitalearth.net.cn/GISRelatedITIssues/XML/IBM-Ten%20best%20bets%20for%20XML%20applications.pdf)